Finding Aid for Lewis Cass papers [microform], 1814-1847
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lewis Cass papers [microform]
1814-1847
Cass, Lewis, 1782-1866.
88154 Aa 2
Official correspondence, notes, and instructions received while serving as U. S. Minister to France and Secretary of War; also official documents of the Michigan Superintendency of Indian Affairs, 1819-1831, and the Office of Indian Affairs, 1814-1817 and 1822-1829, relating in part to Cass's work in negotiating land treaties with the Indians of the Michigan Territory.
60 microfilms
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The microfilm was donated by Nelson Vance Russell (donor no. 487 ) who had acquired the films from the National Archives in the course of his research. The microfilm was acquired in 1946.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Original materials are at the National Archives of the United States.
Lewis Cass was governor of the Michigan Territory, 1813-1831, Secretary of War, 1831-1836, U. S. Minister to France, 1836-1842, U.S. Senator from Michigan, 1845-1856, candidate for President in 1848, and U.S. Secretary of State (1857-1860).
The microfilm was acquired by Professor Nelson Vance Russell in the course of his research on the life of Lewis Cass. The originals of the records are in the National Archives and Records Administration. The files have been arranged by record group number which correspond to the various departments and agencies with whom Cass was associated as territorial governor, as diplomat, or, in the case of the War Department, as Secretary. The series in the collection are: United States Minister to France, United States Secretary of War, Michigan Superintendency of Indian Affairs, and United States Office of Indian Affairs. Cass's work with the Indians as governor of the Michigan Territory is documented in these last two series.
Subjects:
Indians of North America--Michigan.; United States. War Dept.; United States--Foreign relations--France.; United States. Office of Indian Affairs.
- United States Minister to France
  - Dispatches, notes, and miscellaneous letters sent
    - 1836-1842 (Box 1, Reel 1)
      (NARA microcopy no. 14, Roll 1, Vol. 1)
    - 1836-1842 (Box 1, Reel 2)
      (NARA microcopy no. 14, Roll 2, Vol. 2)
    - 1836-1842 (Box 1, Reel 3)
      (NARA microcopy no. 14, Roll 3, Vol. 3)
    - 1836-1842 (Box 1, Reel 4)
      (NARA microcopy no. 14, Roll 4, Vol. 4)
    - 1836-1842 (Box 1, Reel 5)
      (NARA microcopy no. 14, Roll 5)
  - Instructions from the State Department, 1835-1842 (Box 1, Reel 6)
    (NARA microcopy no. 14, Roll 6)
  - Notes from the French Foreign Office, 1835-1842 (Box 1, Reel 7)
    (NARA microcopy no. 14, Roll 7)
  - Consular Letters Received, 1835-1842 (Box 1, Reel 8)
    (NARA microcopy no. 14, Roll 8)
  - Miscellaneous Letters Received, 1835-1842 (Box 1, Reel 9)
    (NARA microcopy no. 14, Roll 9, Vol. 1)
  - Miscellaneous Letters Received, 1835-1842 (Box 1, Reel 10)
    (NARA microcopy no. 14, Roll 10, Vol. 2)
  - Dispatches from U.S. Ministers to France
    - November 19, 1836-May 6, 1839 (Box 3, Reel 59)
      (NARA copy 34, roll 31)
    - May 21, 1839-March 7, 1843 (Box 3, Reel 60)
      (NARA copy 34, roll 32)
- United States Secretary of War
  - Register of Letters Received
    - 1831 (Box 1, Reel 11)
      (NARA microcopy 22, Roll 28, Vol. 28)
    - 1831 (Box 1, Reel 12)
      (NARA microcopy 22, Roll 29, Vol. 29)
    - 1831-1832 (Box 1, Reel 13)
      (NARA microcopy 22, Roll 30, Vol. 30)
    - August-September 1832, 1831 (Box 1, Reel 14)
      (NARA microcopy 22, Roll 31, Vol. 31)
    - 1832-1833, 1831 (Box 1, Reel 15)
      (NARA microcopy 22, Roll 32, Vol. 32)
    - May-December 1833 (Box 1, Reel 16)
      (NARA microcopy 22, Roll 33, Vol. 33)
    - January-August 1834 (Box 1, Reel 17)
      (NARA microcopy 22, Roll 34, Vol. 34)
    - April-December 1834 (Box 1, Reel 18)
      (NARA microcopy 22, Roll 35, Vol. 35)
    - January-August 1835 (Box 1, Reel 19)
      (NARA microcopy 22, Roll 36, Vol. 36)
    - September-December 1835 (Box 1, Reel 20)
      (NARA microcopy 22, Roll 37, Vol. 37)
    - January-March 1836 (Box 2, Reel 21)
      (NARA microcopy 22, Roll 38, Vol. 38)
    - March-May 1836 (Box 2, Reel 22)
      (NARA microcopy 22, Roll 39, Vol. 39)
    - June-September 1836 (Box 2, Reel 23)
      (NARA microcopy 22, Roll 40, Vol. 39)
    - October 1836-February 1837 (Box 2, Reel 24)
      (NARA microcopy 22, Roll 41, Vol. 41)
  - Letters Sent
    - August 1830-1833 (Box 2, Reel 25)
      (NARA microcopy 6, Roll 13)
    - 1834-February 1835 (Box 2, Reel 26)
      (NARA microcopy 6, Roll 14)
    - January-May 1836 (Box 2, Reel 27)
      (NARA microcopy 6, Roll 15)
    - May-December 1836 (Box 2, Reel 28)
      (NARA microcopy 6, Roll 16)
  - Confidential and Unofficial Letters Sent
    - November 1814-August 1835 (Box 2, Reel 29)
      (NARA microcopy 7, Roll 1)
    - September 1835-April 1847 (Box 2, Reel 30)
      (NARA microcopy 7, Roll 2)
- Michigan Superintendency of Indian Affairs
  - Letters Received by the Superintendents
    - Calendar Year, 1819 (Box 2, Reel 32)
    - Calendar Year, 1820 (Box 2, Reel 33)
    - January 1-June 30, 1821 (Box 2, Reel 34)
    - July-December 31, 1821 (Box 2, Reel 35)
    - January 1-June 30, 1822 (Box 2, Reel 36)
    - July-December 31, 1822 (Box 2, Reel 37)
    - January 1-June 30, 1823, July 1-August 16, 1824 (Box 2, Reel 38)
    - July 1-December 31, 1823 (Box 2, Reel 39)
    - January 1-June 30, 1824 (Box 2, Reel 40)
    - August 17-December 31, 1824 (Box 3, Reel 41)
    - January 1-June 30, 1825 (Box 3, Reel 42)
    - July 1-December 31, 1825 (Box 3, Reel 43)
    - January 1-June 30, 1826 (Box 3, Reel 44)
    - July 1-December 31, 1826 (Box 3, Reel 45)
    - January 1-June 30, 1827 (Box 3, Reel 46)
    - July 1-December 31, 1827 (Box 3, Reel 47)
    - January 1-May 31, 1828 (Box 3, Reel 48)
    - June 1-December 31, 1828 (Box 3, Reel 49)
    - January 1-June 30, 1829 (Box 3, Reel 50)
    - July 1-December 31, 1829 (Box 3, Reel 51)
    - January 1-July 31, 1830 (Box 3, Reel 52)
    - August 1-December 31, 1830 (Box 3, Reel 53)
    - January 1-August 26, 1831 (Box 3, Reel 54)
      (end of reel also includes miscellaneous speeches at treaty councils, 1814-1825)
- United States Office of Indian Affairs
  - Records, 1814-1823 (Box 3, Reel 55)
  - Field papers, Sault Ste. Marie Agency, 1822-1829; microfilm negative (Box 3, Reel 56)
  - Letters sent to Sault Ste. Marie Agency, etc., 1826; microfilm negative (Box 3, Reel 57)
  - Letters sent to Sault Ste. Marie Agency, etc., 1828; microfilm negative (Box 3, Reel 58)